Lowell Thomas Film Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
- 2. Alaska, 1942-1968; 471 cans
  - R1 Alaska, High Adventure With Lowell Thomas, 1957; 347 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 158)
    The film showed a landscape view of mountains, it showed a plane taking off, it showed sea divers and it showed men sliding down poles. The film showed Lowell Thomas standing and talking. It also showed other men at a table talking and looking at something. It showed someone getting a hair cut, showed people playing instruments and it showed people climbing up a ladder.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Alfleaver family to go fishing; Taking crab out of pot aboard boat, 255 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 159)
    Crab fishermen pulling large cages of [Alaskan] crabs onboard. A bear catches a salmon form a river. Crab fishermen at work.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Alaska Crab Last Pos Cuts, 283 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 160)
    Men on a boat, crab walking on the sea floor. [Alaska?] Fishermen looking for crab, pulling in nets and cages. Bears playing. A dog eating. A family eating dinner. A team processing the crab meat to be shipped.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. Introduction, 1943; linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 161)
    A - Showed Lowell Thomas Jr. talking and it showed him spinning a globe (90ft; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. Introduction, 1943; linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 162)
    B (negative), C- Introduction of fun and adventure. The man talking to didn't specify to whether he was talking the Thomas Senior or Thomas Junior (45ft), D- Same audio as C (45ft)"; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. Introduction, 1943; linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 163)
    C- Introduction of fun and adventure. 45ft), D- Same audio as C (45ft)"; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. Introduction, 1943; linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 164)
    D- Same audio as C (45ft)"; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Glacier Falling, 25 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 176)
    A boat sailing on rough water. A closeup of a crab. A crab trap being lifted up by a crane.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Climbing Mountain, 1960; 163 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 903)
    The film showed a group of men sitting at table. The film also showed people skiing and walking up snow mountains.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Ext. Wakefield & General Aloha; Salmon; Wakefield Boys Fishing (on film frames), 102 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 917)
    Two young boys fish by a creek. In church, a priest blesses a group of teenage boys.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Girl's Rifle Team, 1961; 121 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 919)
    The film showed women holding guns. One of them were laying on her stomach in the floor while the other lady was standing up. They were both being supervised by another man as they were shooting the gun.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Mountain landscapes, skiing, airplanes, planes landing in water, aerial views of mountains, etc., 1946; 315 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1075)
    The film starts off with people getting ready to ski then it cuts to beach sunset then it cuts back to people skiing. It showed a man skiing with sled dogs and it showed two men sorting items out. The film showed landscape shot of snow mountains and showed a man with a camera. The film showed melting ice water and then it showed people loading things on to a plane and then the plane flew off and was flying around then started to drop things off it to men that was on the ground that needed the items.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Glacier Falling, 17 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1119)
    Flowers in a garden. A boy standing on a beach. Three bears walking. Men on a boat. Crabs in a trap.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - High Adventure with Lowell Thomas Alaska, 86 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1122)
    LTJ walking with military man down stairs in gardens, close up of gold garden statues - lion, man on horseback - LTJ and military man talking outside in garden, interior shots of LTJ with men and tiger skin, man playing drums.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Alaska Crab King, 1960; 712 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1136)
    Alternating short scenes of a classroom and preparing/cooking/eating Alaska king crabs, divided by leader. Final, longest scene are king crabs crawling around in the ocean.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Adaq King of Alaska Seas, 668 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1137)
    Lowell Thomas, Jr. introduces film "Adak: King of the Alaskan Seas", then interviews Lowell [Wakefield] about winter crab fishing and their Russian and Japanese competition.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Adaq King of Alaska Seas, 950 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1138)
    Lowell Thomas, Jr. narrates "Adak: King of the Alaskan Seas", where he witnesses a Russian Orthodox wedding before following a crab fisherman from catching to processing the meat to eating it.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Alaskan Crab King, 1960; 1000 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1139)
    Various scenes from "Adak: King of the Alaskan Seas" (a film about fishing for king crab in Alaska), separated by leader.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: additional pieces in can; Type: Positive
  - Alaskan Crab King, 1960; 1000 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1140)
    Various scenes from "Adak: King of the Alaskan Seas" (a film about fishing for king crab in Alaska), separated by leader.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: There are few scenes not big enough to be spliced with the rest of the film; Type: Positive
  - Chamber of Commerce Alaska America's Brightest Star Neg Cuts, 1961; 1200 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1141)
    Various scenes from around Alaska separated by leader. Scenes include Governor William A. Egan, Inuits in traditional garments, Mary Taylor "Tay Thomas", landscapes, the Anchorage, and more.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Chamber of Commerce Alaska America's Brightest Star; Rolls: AA, AB, AC, AD, AE, AF, AG, 1958-1962; 434 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1142)
    Film showed a landscape view of mountains, ice rocks and a river. It showed a forested area, showed children at school on a playground, showed man controlling a wood cutter, showed people sitting down outside while a fire was burning and a few of the people were playing some type of instrument. The film showed a city area and cars were waiting on the stoplight to change to green. The film showed four little children being photographed by a woman, it showed worker connecting steel pipes, it showed a sled dog race that had a lot of people gathered around. The film showed four people exiting a house, it showed seaplanes and it showed people dressed in costumes that look like Native Americans and they were also conducting a play. The film also showed people getting ready to ski, it showed crabs underwater, showed little kids in a classroom, it showed cows and it showed a women carrying a baby in baby sac on her back.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Chamber of Commerce Alaska America's Brightest Star Neg Cuts, 1960; 450 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1143)
    A man cutting down a tree. A sunrise. Logs floating on a river. Wood chips being processed. People landing in parachutes on a tarmac. A marina. Aerial footage of a farm. Two men hunting in a marsh. A U.S. Airforce plane landing. A ski slope, a sign reads "My Ayeska Ski and Recreation". An Eskimo woman dances. Planes flying in formation. A dog sled race in Anchorage. A man fishing, a sign reads "Welcome to Kulik River. Anglers Paradise". An army helicopter landing. Students in a classroom. Glaciers. Eskimos using a handheld trampoline to lift each other into the air on a beach at sunset.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Alaska Last frontier Part 1, 1945; linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1144)
    Totempole, men and women, buildings, church, bear and bird, plane in desert, aerial of port, market, woman laundry, man with hat and bow, street, poster, guns, confederate flag, "prehistoric writing," woman playing piano, shoes, men in cave, men eating/sleeping, child; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color, Black & White; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - "The Last Frontier" Alaska, 1943; 948 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1145)
    "High Adventure with Lowell Thomas." (Audio only.) Lowell speaks to us from "inside a crevice in the ice." He tells is that the 49th state is home to to the World's largest carnivorous animal: the brown bear. He goes on to explain to us the different customs of an Eskimo tribe, and the differences between them and other tribes. He talks about different transportation opportunities. (How we can get to and from the state and how we can get to different locations within the state.) Up-to-date farming ensures the best foods will get shipped to local supermarkets. He takes us to a ragtime-themed restaurant. We listen to the songs they play. He is with scientists studying a deep crevice in a glacier. The scientists say it is important to study icebergs because it is a good indication of what the weather will be like in the future. Lowell Thomas interviews a helicopter pilot from inside a helicopter. The pilot explains that his job is very safe because he has a very qualified rescue team.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Chamber of Commerce Alaska America's Brightest Star Neg Cuts, 1942; 555 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1146)
    We are shown a map of Alaska. Two fighter jets fly in unison. Two planes take off with parachutes lagging behind them. Eskimo men carve stones. Close up of Lowell Thomas Jr. speaking to the camera. Men ski and weave between flags. A woman and children shop in the produce section of a grocery store. A man stands next to a giant head of lettuce and a giant radish. Men exit a Weir Alaska plane and are greeted by Alaskan dancers. Men cut down trees and pull them with a rope. A man climbs up a tree by wrapping a rope around a truck. Close up of an oil drill. We are shown a totem pole. Cut to a shot of the American flag. Words appear on the screen: "This has been a presentation of Alaska Bankers Association, Alaska state Chamber of Commerce." Cut to a shot of a totem pole. Screen: Alaska, America's Brightest Star.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Chamber of Commerce Alaska America's Brightest Star Neg Cuts, 1959; 373 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1147)
    A man stands at the top of a tree he just climbed. Men load chopped down trees onto trucks. Cut to a baked bean factory. Hunters hide in tall grass and aim for an animal they are pointing to. Fishermen pull up cages full of Alaskan crab. Brief shots of men skiing. We see blue-ribbon winning giant lettuce and radish.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. Alaska - America's Brightest Star Mag. Narration, 1052 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1148)
    Audio only. We hear snippets of narration for a documentary about Alaska. He begins with talking about the Alaskan gold rush. "Alaska: America's Brightest Star." He describes a town fish wheel that can catch 400 salmon a day. The Eskimos make fur parkas made of seal skin. He describes a bull Moose and it's calf. He explains to us how oil is Alaska's newest and brightest industry. A man conducts an orchestra. Indian dancers reenact a dramatic story in which their chief is killed by a bear. He tells us that the Supermarket imports food from everywhere for the Alaskan housewife. Fresh bear tracks leading into a meadow. The hunters miss their chance to shoot the bear.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. Alaska-America's Brightest Star Mag. Dialogue Track, 647 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1149)
    Audio of what sounds like natives singing, chanting and banding on drums.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Vinegar syndrome - Pioneer Alaskan King Crab, Scenes 5, 70, 43, 34, 62, 65, 90, 88, 40, 47, 54, 98, 42, 59B, 33, 9, 35, 82, 58, 36, 76, 39, 60, 45, 61, 64, 66, 63, 16, 1959; 421 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1150)
    The film showed a traditional wedding, it showed a little boy and then it showed men on a boat. The film also showed a snow area, it showed a crab, it showed two little children picking up sea shells. The film also showed cows, a man fixing a car, showed another man drinking tea or coffee on a sail boat and it also showed a map.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Look North! Work Print Picture University of Alaska Lowell Thomas Jr., 1942; 573 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1151)
    Students line up in their graduation caps and gowns. A man speaks to us from behind a desk. Scientists work with students in a lab. We are shown a map of Alaska. Sign: "Douglas Marine Station of the University of Alaska." We see icebergs collapsing. Men sail by the glaciers in a boat. We see whale tails peaking out of the water. Men pull sea urchins out of shallow pools of water. they then collect a sample of sand. Cut to a college basketball game. Teachers watch over a kindergarten class. Cows line up in a barn to be milked. We see ferrets in cages. Men and women try mining for gold using silver pans.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. University of Alaska, Work Print Picture Look North!, 1942; 1017 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1152)
    Leader: "University of Alaska." Men on boats watch ice bergs collapse. Cut to men and women panning for gold. Title: "University of Alaska presents Look North!" Graduates in caps and gowns walk towards a stage. Cut to the President of the University speaking to the camera from his desk. Scientists inspect sea animals. They find large a large crab and stick it in their bucket. Cut to miners shoveling dirt into a cart. Cut to a college basketball game. We are shown all sorts of wildlife and animals. Sign: Arctic Research Laboratory. Scientists observe jars of water. Cut to men sitting in class listening to a professor. We see the Northern Lights shining over a school building. A giant satellite is pointed towards the sky.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. University of Alaska Mag. Dialogue Track A Look North!, 523 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1153)
    A man was talking about outer space, polo cap research station and there was music playing in the end.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - University of Alaska Work Units, 530 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1154)
    Audio film started off with music playing and then you hear man talking about wind storm and said how they are not too far from the North pole. He also talks about the arctic ocean, the Russians and he talks about research projects and he gave longitude and latitude coordinates.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Capital Cities Rolls 01A-03A Track, Moviola #36, 1063 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1155)
    Outdoor ambient sounds.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Alaska Studio Radar Talk, linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1156)
    VS - no leader, shrunk; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Alaska Studio Radar Talk p 101 212, linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1157)
  - Alaska Last Frontier Reel 1 Composite Print, 542 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1158)
    Tape A.A. Birds chirping. The sound of moving elephants. A baby elephant is captured by the group. Previously they had a tiger then released it. A bear growls.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Alaska Last Frontier Reel 1 Composite Print, 617 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1159)
    CC Copeland and King talking while with a Rhino. A recording of the group as it observes a Rhino roll on its side. They capture it. Also observing elephants and describe the teeth of a animal they captured.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Adaq: King of Alaskan Seas, 1961; 1200 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1160)
    "ADAQ: King of Alaskan Seas". Directed by Michael D. Murray. Narrated by Lowell Thomas, Jr. Presented by Wakefield Fisheries. Many scenes on a large fishing boat and of snow and ice.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Adaq: King of Alaskan Seas, 946 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1161)
    "ADAQ: King of Alaskan Seas". Directed by Michael D. Murphy. Produced, written, and narrated by Lowell Thomas, Jr. Presented by Wakefield Fisheries. This film demonstrated the crabbing process, from catching them to processing them to eating them.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color and black and white; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - University of Alaska Pos Cuts, 392 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1162)
    On the audio track people was talking about Great Britain, Russia, France and Germany. They were talking about the balance of power and that Europe was table until the Franco Prussian war. They also talked about problems in terms of international politics and unsettled situations. They also talked about Cuba, and Castro having large plantations such as sugar plantations and the he had peasants from South America who worked for him. They also talked about communism, fascism, democracy and dictatorship. One person said ambition must be made to counteract ambition. They talked about what the world would of been like if Hitler had conquered all of Europe. They also talked about the allied powers and that they waited to long to protect the nation. Someone also talked about biological science, physical science and scientific programs. Someone then talked about Alaska being the key stone, talked about the University of Alaska and that it holds the purpose of becoming a free world center for all baisc aspects of arctic research and study.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - University of Alaska Pos Cuts, 895 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1163)
    Reports given to CARL radio, or the Arctic Research Lab Station. Reports given form stations in London, Switzerland, and the North Pole.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - High adventure, Campus refunt?, 1960; 693 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1164)
    The film showed a man talking on a CB radio and then it showed outside of an building with people walking out the building. The film showed 4 men walking, showed a man sitting down talking, showed a man operating a tractor. The film showed people walking in water, it showed men and women sitting down and it showed a landscape shot of building and houses and it showed ice glaciers falling.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - University of Alaska, 1942; 558 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1165)
    Opens with a map of Alaska. Cut to a man playing piano in an orchestra. Scientists take soil samples from the ground. A young woman aims a gun towards a target.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Anchorage, 935 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1166)
    Mostly Lowell Thomas, other people, and the Boeing Alaska Airlines Golden Nugget Jet, but also has some footage of people at a crowded beach.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - BIA-Kids, Camera Trouble-NG Roll 38-39-40, 1961; 1007 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1167)
    Children smelling and picking flowers in a field. The northern lights. A graduation ceremony. Kids playing outside a suburban home. A man hunting in Alaska. Footage of the Arctic Research Laboratory. People playing instruments. A college campus. People dog-sledding. Various scenes of Alaska.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - University of Alaska Ice Island Pos Cuts, 1961; 823 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1168)
    We are shown aspects of the University of Alaska's science department. Scientists work in the lab. Cut to men making speeches at a graduation. Three men go hiking. They collect dirt samples and nurture a baby duck. A girl protects her aim with a gun. We are shown the layout of the University's campus.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - University Commencement Footage, University of Alaska, "Reaching for the Stars", Lowell Thomas Jr., 931 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1169)
    The film showed a group of graduates walking and it also showed a graduation ceremony with Lowell Thomas being one of the graduates. Five different men gave a speech including Lowell Thomas. The film showed people getting diplomas and their masters. Also showed the graduates turning their tassels to the other side to signify that they have Graduated from the University of Alaska. The film showed people with their family and friends after the graduation ceremony.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - University of Alaska Orig. Cuts, 468 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1170)
    We are shown satellites pointing towards the sky. Different shots of University of Alaska and rural Alaska. Cut to women playing violin as part of an orchestra. A choir sings behind the orchestra. Students in class listen to their professor lecture.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - University of Alaska Orig. Cuts, 502 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1171)
    Two men drill a hole underground. Cut to a shot of the Northern Lights. Alaskans pan for gold in the river. Scientists conduct research in the Arctic.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color, Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - University of Alaska, 1961; 752 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1172)
    The film showed a snow blower blowing snow, it showed a tractor pulling something out of water, it showed a landscape shot of mountains from plane view, it showed a plane taking off. The film showed a man talking, it showed people on a boat, it showed a man talking on a CB radio. It showed people walking on in snow, showed people skiing, showed children playing, showed a plane flying over a forested area. The film also showed a man pouring something in a jar and it showed men taking things off a plane.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - University of Alaska, 1961; 824 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1173)
    The film showed a plane flying, showed ice glaciers falling, showed ice mountains, showed a man talking to another man. The film showed a U.S flag, showed vessel ship, showed people on a boat, showed an orchestra, showed a snow tractor, showed a man shoveling snow off a roof. The film showed a lift. The film showed a landscape shot of mountains, showed people climbing up a rock that is compacted with snow. The film showed men pulling up a bucket and it showed a gun in the snow.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - University of Alaska Pos Cuts, 993 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1174)